[SPEAKER_01]: So Ajahn, I've heard you talk a lot about discerning things not being in my control, and I think I do see this to some extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: What still confuses me a bit, though, is how exactly this translates to making one not identify with those things, or to release from suffering, to be released from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: For instance,
[SPEAKER_01]: I know I can't control my body, but I still find myself identifying with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't control my feelings, but I still feel like I'm the one feeling them.
[SPEAKER_01]: I didn't choose my character traits, but still they make me who I am.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there a step I am missing, or am I not seeing the lack of control on the right level?
[SPEAKER_00]: Both.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're not seeing the lack of control on the right level, because if you do,
[SPEAKER_00]: Unidentification with those things will be automatic.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, it would be the result of your seeing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You wouldn't have to then... Well, I need to see things that are not in my control and now I need to also unidentify myself with them.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seeing that it's not in your control means you you cannot be identified with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, eh... Basically, the problem is that your idea of non-control is abstract.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why, practically, you are still very much identified with things, because, practically, you still seek pleasure in your body, you still find safety in your possessions, and, fundamentally, you do not see the peril and the danger of those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you want to contemplate the non-control rightly, like, of course, you can get information and think about the aspects of non-control, but that's pretty much abstract.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to contemplate non-control?
[SPEAKER_00]: Contemplate the danger in things that you've taken to be yours, that you control, the peril, the danger of losing them, the danger of them changing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in regard to your own body, contemplate the terminal illness, death and these things, and even if you don't think in terms of non-control, you will be very much experiencing the non-control on that emotional level.